Why this lectures
on edge computing and cloud architecture.
It's a hybrid,
a closed approach to modern applications
instead of just putting everything
in the edge, everything in the cloud.
We're going to talk
about a hybrid approach.
But before we do, let's talk
about some simple definitions.
Cloud computing on demand highly scalable
typically public.
But we need to talk public and private.
It abstracts away physical infrastructure.
So everything is, managed
through software defined infrastructure.
Edge computing is almost the opposite.
Everything's decentralized.
I know where nodes are.
They have meaning,
when they're out there,
they could be mobile,
edge nodes, fixed edge nodes.
There's lots of things out there.
The goal with edge computing and pushing
compute out to the edge is minimizing
latency, saving bandwidth and decreasing
costs and increasing reliability.
If we can.
Right.
Motivation for hybrid architectures.
I want to, because
we've had such a big explosive growth in,
IoT and edge sensors and edge computing,
we need some way of managing all this data
that's being generated.
And there is a lot of data
So why not do some of the work on the edge
where the data is
and only pass up into the cloud?
The data that's required to do aggregation
or to do higher level
analytics that I need to do.
I this is a balancing point
that I have between regulatory
and cost and benefits.
So a lot of times
this is not a technical decision
as much as it is
a business decision that I have to make.
So these are a lot of things
that you have to weigh as an architect.
All right.
Let's talk about just high level
view of the cloud architecture.
Very simple. My physical layer.
That's obviously the physical things
I can touch in the data center racks, data
centers, network equipment, compute nodes,
storage nodes, all that stuff.
Virtualization layer,
all the cloud service providers
use different virtualization layers,
whether they're hypervisors for VMs
or their container,
clouds
that are out there that are using Docker
or one of the other, systems
that are out there.
Then on top of that virtualization layer,
I have a management orchestration layer
that is managing that software
defined infrastructure,
spinning up storage network, compute.
That's the management orchestration layer.
And then I have my middle,
middleware services
where I've got databases and message
busses and, you know, all the things
and monitoring I did identity management
systems, all the things that are there
to support the top layer,
which is the application layer, right?
The application layer.
The job there is
that's where I'm writing my code.
And I'm taking advantage
of the middleware, the orchestration,
the virtualization layer
in the physical layer. Right.
So that's the idea behind cloud.
I only focus on the application layer.
All the other stuff is handled for me
in the cloud.
That's the idea behind it.
Huge benefits in cloud.
We've talked about this in other lectures.
Elasticity, global distribution.
Managed services.
I don't have to worry about them.
I can pay as I go
so I can spin up a thousand machines
and tear them down,
and I only pay for the time I use
instead of having a thousand machines
sitting in my data center that I spend
a lot of capital expenditures on, right?
Common challenges
that we have with cloud latency
sometimes, user
experience can be kind of there
if I've got bad latency,
egress, bandwidth costs.
Moving data out of the cloud is expensive.
We've got regional outages
that can cause problems.
And then sometimes
I have some compliance issues
where where the data is actually
stored really matters.
Edge computing.
Let's talk about edge,
drivers behind edge, ultra low latency.
If I need to have a, read a sensor
and I need it to react immediately,
let's say at a nuclear power plant,
I don't know that I want, all my data
going up to a cloud
to be analyzed
before I turn off a nuclear reactor.
I want that stuff, you know, close, close.
And so the key drivers there are ultra low
latency requirements, bandwidth savings.
If I'm generating a lot of data
instead of, processing out in the cloud,
maybe I process part of it, locally first
and then send stuff up to the cloud.
And if I'm worried about data privacy
and local processing, things like that,
those are some things that I could most
definitely do at the edge.
There are lots of different types
of, edge nodes out there.
Device nodes, like phones and cameras,
wearables, things like that.
Even a laptop is a device edge
or I have got local edge.
This could be a micro data center
or a gateway or an edge appliance.
That's sitting there, at a location
I can have regional edge
devices, where, maybe in a factory.
I have, multiple buildings in a factory.
And the factory is a regional edge
and the local edge of the,
in each building type of thing.
So you have this aggregation of, of edge,
and then I've got, the cloud
service providers know that, hey,
I want to be part of this edge revolution.
So they've created
these cloud edge services
that allow me to start moving data
into the edge.
And these architectures
that are built around that.
Edge architectures
are a little bit different than cloud,
because cloud is all about unification
and putting everything,
more homogeneous, even though I may have
heterogeneous background, hardware,
I want as much homogeneity
as possible in the edge.
I'm dealing with heterogeneous.
I'm dealing with disconnected part time
running things.
It's so the architecture
is a little bit different,
but there's a lot of similarity.
And having a control plane
and a workload manager type of thing.
One of the key differences in edge is
I have to deal with data
a lot more effectively than in the cloud.
And the cloud storage
is the big massive storage, right?
It's accessible everywhere on the edge.
That's not the case.
And I don't necessarily want all my edge
data available everywhere.
So your data plane becomes important.
Typically you'll have an edge
agent running on the individual edge,
giving me health metrics and runtime
statistics and things like that.
Also, with the edge,
you have to be concerned
about physical security
as well as, logical or cyber security.
Right.
Your data is out there.
It's close to where people can touch it.
So encryption,
local encryption is important.
Leveraging TPMs for secure elements,
secure boot, firmware verification,
validation, things like that.
So managing those edge devices
ends up being, extremely important.
If I start looking at,
hybrid architectures,
cloud edge architectures,
there's some similarities in,
the management plane of microservices.
For example,
if I've developed those correctly,
I can take advantage
of those microservices
and they can easily move between things.
But I have to have some common
functionality across my edge and my core,
and that's that orchestration layer
and a virtualization layer.
All right.
So having those figured out
and having a match
between cloud and edge become important.
The other interesting thing
that you have to deal with
is data management across across all this.
So it's a little bit different
when you're talking these hybrid
because now I'm managing do I move data.
Do I move applications. How do I do it.
We see a lot more message bus passing
between this
as the number of nodes increases,
as the complexity can increase without
putting something like a message bus,
like a pub StubHub, like Kafka or Pulsar
or Rabbit MQ in in the middle there.
So I think the integration patterns
are different because I'm dealing with
tens of thousands of heterogeneous nodes
that can drop in and out continuously.
So understanding those design patterns
ends up being important.
Lots of really cool use cases out there,
that continue to grow like, AR and VR,
where I need latency.
That would be horrible
if I had a screen on my eyes
and I was waiting on the
on the cloud service providers.
Because that computes so far away.
Let's put the compute
right in the goggles,
and do some edge, rendering,
instead of waiting.
And then push updates up to the cloud.
Right.
So architecting what you put in the cloud
and what you keep on the edges
is really important.
Health care monitoring a big deal.
We see this with smart beds and wearables
and things like that.
I'm doing a lot of processing on the edge,
and I'm always sending up,
things into the cloud as needed.
Right. Retail and smart buildings.
Another great, edge to cloud case
where I can have a building.
I can have a set of buildings on a campus,
I can run aggregation nodes,
I can have a whole company
with everything managed, locally.
But also up in the cloud.
So I do some things local
and some things up in the cloud, where
I get a big picture view of everything,
but I can make things happen.
Locally autonomous vehicles.
Can you imagine
autonomous vehicles that
relied on the cloud to drive?
We'd have accidents all over the place.
Latency problems.
So really, we need some control
in, in the car itself.
And then,
you know, obviously pushing up telemetry.
Specific telemetry up into the cloud
could give me a bigger picture
on, you know, what's going on
with all the vehicles in my fleet.
So understanding
where your data is, where it needs to be
and where decisions are made
and where they need to react to,
is key to developing,
these types of architectures.
Okay.
So because the
because there isn't a one design pattern
that fits everything
coming up with your architecture,
you should be leaning
on a lot of the design patterns
for distributed computing
and understand all the key factors
in making those design decisions.
Resource
constraints are a big deal, right?
How much do I have?
How much resource do I have at the edge?
Do I have, a specialized accelerators
that can handle the type of workload
I have at the edge?
If the answer is no, then
maybe I need to go up in the cloud, right?
Or you got to look at cost.
How much does it cost to put
that specialized,
acceleration in the edge
if it's cost prohibitive?
So there's a lot of things you've got,
you got to weigh here, right?
Also use minimal base images
as much as you can on the edge.
Also in the cloud too, right.
If you're using containers,
use alpine distros.
They're very small, lightweight
and very secure.
That's the idea.
Decrease your attack footprint.
Also look at ways
that you can use, automation
for deployment
and management of these solutions.
They can be very tough to manage.
Because you are talking about distributing
across thousands of nodes.
There a lot of time there isn't one pane
of glass that you can do this through.
There are some frameworks
that are starting to emerge
that can help with that,
but you still need a way of distributing
and use, best practices in DevOps around,
you know, rolling
updates and things like that.
Make sure that you
look at security and compliance,
especially with the edge devices.
Make sure you have hardware root of trust
so I can trust where I'm getting data
from, where I'm pushing data to out
in, in the edge.
Make sure that you do have,
policy engines
that can, to local reinforcement of,
policies,
add in the edge device
itself, use as many open standards
as you can to break down
some of that heterogeneity problem.
So I can have better protocols.
I can have consistent protocols
coming back and doing analytics.
All right.
Some really interesting
things that we're starting to see,
to push machine
learning down into the edge.
We're having TensorFlow Lite
or tiny machine learning.
And with NPA's, neuromorphic processors,
we're seeing a lot more that can happen
way down deep inside the edge.
We're also seeing 5G
and then 6V6G coming up
in the future
where bandwidth will be even greater.
So now that opens up more opportunities
for for me
to even move more stuff at lower latency.
We're seeing some interesting things
with serverless at the edge, where they've
put in a full management orchestration
plan for you, which works out really good.
And then, there's some federated
learning models across multiple nodes.
There's some more really cool distributed,
architectures that are out there
that you should be looking at.
So if you want to, you can go out and take
a look at federated versus centralized,
AI training.
Great research out there.
That might be worth, taking a look at.
All right.
Remember cloud is about scale
analytics of aggregated data.
Edge responsiveness local processing
I can do if I
the decision needs to be made local
where the data is collected.
Move it to the edge if you possibly can
and then use that hybrid approach.
Identify where you need to move data,
where decisions are made
and where the decision makers are.